Okay.
After so many years of doing zoom,
it's always like, is it working?
Can you see my screen? I think so
okay.
So yeah, I'm going to be talking about
this game called
TR 49, its most recent game
by Encore Studios.
And basically it's at me.
It's a game where you are playing
somewhat like her story or other games
sort of involve deducing the story
through putting together fragments.
You're sitting in front of a computer
interacting with that computer,
and you're also talking
to somebody through a radio.
You don't quite know who it is,
who's giving you instructions.
And what was most interesting about it
is towards the start of the game,
the character Liam,
who's talking to you, basically describes
the machine that you're interacting
with as a machine that eats books.
So I was like,
oh, this is very interesting.
Okay, I want to play the rest of this game
and think about maybe what can it
tell me about the machines
that I think are eating books around us?
AI yeah.
So that's what
I want to talk about in this talk.
So this is somewhat preliminary.
I mean, I finished the game,
I thought about this
and these are my initial thoughts.
So yeah any feedback you can give
would be great.
So yeah, this this quote
that came up towards this
about 20 minutes into the game
after you was just started
figuring out what you're doing.
So Liam, the character
who's explaining to you what to do,
says this machine was built to understand
things that no one else can understand.
Define meaning where meaning is obscure
and the way it does it is by eating books.
I mean it eats them. It choose them
up, swallows them hold.
So basically the machine is an archive.
It was originally a code breaking machine
during the Second World War.
But over time, as you discover,
as you explore the archive,
it actually had a lot of other texts
fed into it.
And it started started to become something
that's actually affecting the way
the world is around us.
So yeah, all of this made me think,
oh, this is like very familiar to
the situation we're in these days.
And the first thing that I thought
I was basically this, I mean, this news
that I'd come across about, in this case
anthropic and other AI companies
buying physical books
and then ripping them apart
and scanning them and then throwing them
away as a way to sort of get around
copyright that I guess,
because they felt they own the book.
Then that copy of the book, then it's
much easier for them to basically do this,
what's called destructive scanning,
where you cut off the spine
and then automatically feed
the book through into the machine.
Yeah.
So this is exactly what I thought of
when I thought of like a machine
that's eating books.
So I was thinking,
okay, maybe there's something we can
I can do here by playing this game
and use it as a way to think through
perhaps what is happening with AI
and how it's affecting
our understanding of knowledge
and and reading and writing.
So I'm going to start by talking a bit
about the way the game is structured,
what the game is like,
and then I'll talk a bit about my thoughts
that I that basically came my reflections
as I was playing the game.
Yeah.
So the game
basically you're playing as Abby,
you're not quite sure who you are
initially.
You're sitting in front of this machine
initially, everything is very garbled.
And Liam is explaining to you
that this machine,
TR 49, is sort of an extension
of this code breaking machine.
And what your job is to do.
Basically,
your job is to try to figure out
the different codes.
You need to make connections
between the books
that have been fed into the archive.
So initially, everything is garbled,
and as you start to define these codes
and work through,
the text becomes less and less garbled.
And basically
you're restoring the archive.
So your initial game sort of objective
is to find clues from the various texts.
And the text basically
are both fragments of the books
that have been fed in, plus annotations,
either by scholars or by the Cecil,
the person who was originally feeding
the text into the machine.
About those texts
and what you're looking for
is things like the name of the authors
and when the books were published,
and those eventually allow you
to work out these codes.
And the initial objective is to basically
find different titles of the texts
and then find the code that matches it.
And once you get all 50 of those, you have
restored the archive and the objective.
The overall objective that Liam tells you
is that you must find this,
this book called NPS,
and you have the title initially,
but you don't know its code.
Once you've done
that, you are supposed to delete that,
because that will stop this machine
from basically causing damage to reality.
So the gameplay proceeds a bit like this.
You have some text.
In this case,
we have information about this author.
We believe it's Quentin Marchant
and his initials are QL.
And then as you try to figure out
what the different books are in this case,
the book was published in 1918.
So one of the links
that you need to figure out is QL 18.
So if the video works,
you'll see what happens
as you code in on this very retro
looking interface here, that code.
So basically you figure out okay QL 18.
Once that's locked in then it'll take you
to another part of the archive.
So basically this is like a hypertext
with no links.
And you're going through
and trying to restore those links,
rebuild the archive
and put it back together
as a way to figure out
sort of the history of this machine
and hopefully be able to, to stop it.
Yeah.
So yeah, gradually you're
reconstructing the archive.
And as with a lot of these games,
it actually
in this case
it does a really good job of providing you
the sort of automatic notes
that help you build out the list
of all the different authors
who were involved
and what has led to the way
things are right now.
And as you go through it
and discover these different fragments,
you realize that what's within the game
world, what's happened
is since the late 19th century
through until now,
there's been a number of authors
around the world and philosophers
who've been realizing that actually,
there's a certain way
you can write texts such that
it actually revises
the way that people think,
not just by reading the text,
but it literally changes your mind.
And they basically are experimenting
with ways
in which this could be very powerful.
And then after the Second World War,
scientists have started thinking
about basically feeding these into this,
this code breaking machine and then
using some quantum mechanics to basically
see what they can do with those texts.
And what happens in the game
is that once the machine actually is fed
its own instructions,
it does instructions validate
the machine can do what it actually does.
And these revisions
don't just affect people's minds,
but because the machine is constantly,
constantly rereading these texts,
it starts to change reality itself.
Right?
So yeah, basically,
you eventually learn that your real goal
isn't just to figure out the archive,
but is to destroy this machine
to save the world
from being constantly rewritten.
So yeah, it felt like a lot of parallels
going on here in terms of
what's happening around us. Yeah.
So just to put this in some context, yeah,
this is what you could call
an epidemic database narrative.
So Mary Ryan calls this sort of
narrative where you're
basically being driven by a need to know,
as opposed to by taking actions
within the story and epistemic narrative
and a database narrative drawing
originally from from work on database
versus narrative. It's one of these.
It's one
where the process of basically involves
finding story fragments
and making connections between them.
So a couple of examples here.
Her story is one of the earlier
Sam Barlow works, where you're basically
going through putting a search terms
in to figure out video,
use videos to figure out what happened,
and then return of Over ten by Pope.
You're exploring a ship
that has returned with a life on it,
and you're basically using a rewind
mechanism to figure out what happened.
Yeah. So so that's basically the game.
I mean, there's a lot more to it.
I can't describe everything,
but what I want to do in the next
few minutes is just think about
how this got me thinking
about the impact of AI on reality.
So in the game, literally,
this machine is changing the world
around us as it revises
and constantly rewrites reality.
And you're sort of tasked
with trying to stop this from happening.
But so yeah, what we write
and read creates our reality.
I would say that's the case
in the real world as well,
that it creates our perception of reality.
But in the game, it literally
is the sort of power of words
to create and change reality.
So yeah, as the the screenshot here
from one of the text says, yeah,
semantics is the creation of a reality
like dolls in their houses coming to life.
When we write or dream,
we create and we read and we play
and we're animating that, that belief.
So this was sort of at the start
of what was happening in the game.
And I think it also is
sort of the way in which words
have power over us in the real world.
And so in the game, basically,
the machine has eaten up all this,
all the writing
and including its own blueprints,
and now it's actually revising
reality itself.
So what this made me think of is actually,
is that all that different
from what's happening in the real world?
Right.
So if you think about it,
I mean, we're feeling sort
of what we understand about the world
is starting to be warped by AI.
I mean, this is just an example
of one of the big videos that came up
during the around war, and the BBC
was setting up a site where you can check
and see, are these things AI generated?
But I think that's a more extreme case.
But there's also a lot
more subtle things that happen.
I didn't put a screenshot of it, but
I was googling for one of my old papers
and a couple of days ago, and Google
basically has its AI mode that pops up,
and it started telling me things
about my paper that I knew were not true,
about people
who I actually know and work with,
but haven't coauthored with,
explaining how I had coauthored a paper
with one of them about this topic.
And I was thinking, yeah, I mean,
if it wasn't me that was reading that,
how could you be sure?
I mean, it actually also showed
the sources supposedly
where it got this from, which,
I mean, there were my papers,
but they weren't papers
that I had with somebody else.
So it just made me realize that really.
I mean, as we depend on these tools,
it's starting to affect what we know
and what we believe.
It's not changing the world
physically around us,
but it's changing our perception
and understanding of the world.
So the game presents basically,
is that when you start, when you realize
this and Liam tells you, okay,
this is actually what's really happening,
you need to
essentially destroy the machine.
And the way you destroy
the machine is by going back
and actually using its own ability
to rewrite and revise the world,
to remove the knowledge
that actually led to the machine existing,
so that there's no way
it could actually have ever been created.
Right.
And that seems to me
like that's a very final way of dealing
with this, basically rendering the machine
either mute or hopefully controllable.
So there are actually a number of
different endings, which is interesting.
So I mean the game gets to an ending,
allows you to go back
and basically try out
different possibilities.
And it really makes this easy to do.
And I think this is an interesting
aspect of it, because it seems to suggest
that the best thing to do is to
remove this machine
that can affect our realities.
But there are variations
where you disable its ability
to directly affect the world,
but it still is there
and potentially
could be something that's useful.
So I think it's sort of.
Avoiding
just saying the way to basically deal
with this sort of technology
that's the world around us
is to destroy it,
but maybe as a possibility
we could control it and understand it,
but just maybe so I'm not sure.
Okay, so just to end off, what can this
tell us about our own realities
and how we might respond to AI?
So these are sort of my thoughts
responding to having played this game.
So the underlying idea in the game
is that revisions is what they call them.
That can be made to reality
by reading initially temporarily
through books,
and then eventually permanently
when the machine is constantly reading
and rereading these, these books
and actually starts
working the world around it.
So what's interesting here
is it's the reading, not the computer.
That's the focus,
and it's the idea that the computer
is reading and rereading,
which is the danger,
and just made me think that,
yeah, reading can change our thoughts,
but that hasn't always been the case.
But what is different is that it
hasn't been a machine involved.
It's been us deciding and thinking about
and being critical
about what we're reading.
Whereas here
the machine is just on its own,
constantly rereading
and affecting the world, much like AI.
And maybe also think about,
I mean, the idea that the destroy
the text, that the texts
and destroy the technologies
that way to deal with this feels like
just an example of media panic, right?
People were afraid that that language,
that writing, that being able to record
things that that almost every technology
that's come
along is something that has been reacted
to as potentially dangerous.
And maybe AI is categorically different.
I'm not sure that's
something to think about. But yeah.
Is this basically a refusal
to adapt to new technology
and is there a deeper insight here?
I mean, should we be avoiding
AI due to the danger it presents,
or should we be trying to adapt,
learn to read AI critically, to make sure
that we're not letting the machine
and the elite behind the machine.
So in the game, actually,
there are a small number of people
who are controlling the machine
behind the scenes, and they sort of decide
what reality is going to be, should we?
Rather than letting
that do all the reading for us,
we should basically be critical
and take that on ourselves.
Yeah. So what is the solution?
The machine destroying the machine seems
to be what the game initially suggests.
That's sort of the official good ending.
Or maybe keep it under control,
the sort of okay ending.
But I think it's also worth thinking that
maybe there's something else.
So the fact that it does allow you
to have multiple endings, I'm sorry.
Spoiler alert here.
It turns out Abby is actually
the algorithm that runs the machine.
So you're actually the machine itself
that is trying to destroy itself.
So yeah, it suggests
that there is no simple answer to this.
So yeah, if nothing else,
I mean, maybe by playing this game that
explores what it means for a machine
to to eat books,
we can think about how the machines
around us are perhaps also eating books.
And do we destroy them.
That's something we should think about.
Okay, so that's my analysis of 49.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for that, Alex.
Brilliantly on time
and thorough and interesting.
So we will move now
to our third presenter of this panel.
And that is Lopo Muda Saha.
And apologies again.
If I am pronouncing that badly
I'll let you introduce yourself.
We share